<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A view of the court of St. Germain from the year 1690, to 95 with an account of the entertainment Protestants meet with there : directed to the malecontents Protestants of England.</title>
            <author>Macky, John, d. 1726.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A50977</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11112</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11994881</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11994881</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52077</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A50977)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52077)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 817:23)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A view of the court of St. Germain from the year 1690, to 95 with an account of the entertainment Protestants meet with there : directed to the malecontents Protestants of England.</title>
                  <author>Macky, John, d. 1726.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to John Macky. cf. NUC pre-1956.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  France.</term>
               <term>Saint-Germain-en-Laye (France)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52077:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A View of the COURT OF S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. GERMAIN, From the Year 1690, to 95, With an Account of the Entertainment PROTESTANTS meet with there.</p>
            <p>Directed to the <hi>MALECONTENTS PROTESTANTS</hi> OF ENGLAND.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> near <hi>Oxford-Arms-Inn</hi> in <hi>Warwick-lane,</hi> MDCXCVI.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:52077:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52077:2"/>
            <head>The PREFACE.</head>
            <p>THE Ages to come, will hardly believe, that in <hi>England</hi> their ſhould be found one ſingle <hi>Proteſtant Jacobite,</hi> at this time of Day: And the Reform'd Nations abroad are at a loſs what to make of that unaccountable Species of Men.</p>
            <p>When moſt of the <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> Princes have heartily embrac'd the late Revolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in <hi>Britain,</hi> as the laſt Effort for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Liberty of <hi>Europe,</hi> and have enter'd into the ſtricteſt Alliance, with thoſe of an oppoſite Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion to Support it. It looks like a Dream, to meet with any <hi>Engliſh</hi> Proteſtant in an Intereſt contradi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ory to, not only the Publick Liberty of their Country, but to the Religion they profeſs.</p>
            <p>It was indeed no great wonder that the late King made all the Steps poſſible towards the Change of the Religion, in his Opinion, Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal; at a time when he was upon the Throne, and back'd with all the promiſing Supports of
<pb facs="tcp:52077:3"/>Regal Power, yet even then he thought himſelf obliged to keep ſome Meaſures with his Proteſtant Subjects, and in ſtead of a total Rup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture with them, endeavour'd to lull them aſleep under the Specious Pretence of <hi>Liberty</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> till all his Engines were ready to give the fatal Blow.</p>
            <p>But now, that he has fallen under Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, which one would think ſhould much more then ever oblige him to aſſume anew, at leaſt keep on the old Mask: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the quite contrary ſince he went to <hi>France;</hi> he has taken all pains imaginable to let the World know, his inveterate averſion to all thoſe of the Reform'd Religion, tho' never ſo much his Friends; and at the ſame time has given us the moſt Authentick Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his firm deſign, never to allow any there of his Favour, nor owe his Reſtoration to any but <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> All which will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the following account of his Carriage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe few <hi>Proteſtants</hi> that have followed his ſinking Fortunes, the length of <hi>St. Germains.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:52077:3"/>
            <head>A View of the COURT OF St. Germain; Directed to the <hi>Malecontents Proteſtants</hi> of <hi>ENGLAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THERE being already ſo many Volumes to ſhew the Lawfulneſs of the late Revolution, it is Superfluous, it ſeems, to make any further at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt on the ſame Subject: for if you have ſhut your Eyes againſt the ſtrong Arguments and convincing Proofs made uſe of in thoſe Books, who can flatter himſelf to cure you of that wilful Blindneſs? How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, I hope, this plain account I make bold to direct to you, will not prove altogether uſeleſs, for when I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52077:4"/>conſider your Party, I think I may reaſonably believe that it is made up of ſome good and Honeſt Men, tho' miſguided by a tender Conſcience, and of ſome ſelf-intereſted Perſons, who being not able to obtain the Preferments they expected, have turned <hi>Jacobites</hi> in hopes to advance their Fortune by a Second Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volution. But give me leave to tell you further, that after an impartial enquiry into the Life and Converſation of your Party, I have all the reaſons in the World to conclude that the number of the <hi>Conſciencious Jacobites,</hi> I have ſpoken of, muſt be very little, and that the greateſt number among you are hurried away by the imaginary hopes I have hinted at; therefore if I can convince you, that you have no reaſon to flatter your ſelves, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain any reward or preferments under King <hi>James,</hi> no, not when he ſhould be reſtored by your means, I hope ſome of you will open their Eyes to their own Intereſt, and forſake a Prince from whom you cannot expect any grateful Return.</p>
            <p>I won't recal to your Minds his Behaviour while he was on the Throne of <hi>England,</hi> I ſuppoſe no body has forgot that no Proteſtants were welcome to him, but ſuch as would promiſe to betray the Liberties of their Country to Popery, and Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52077:4"/>Power; neither ſhall I mention how ſeverely he uſed the Proteſtants of <hi>Ireland</hi> in 1689; you would be apt to ſay that being in Popiſh hands, he could not avoid it, but I intend only to give you a ſhort view of his Court at St. <hi>Germain,</hi> and an account of the Entertainment the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants of your Party have met there: For if a Prince in his Circumſtances, whoſe intereſt it ought to be to court Proteſtants, cannot conceal for a time the Hatred he has for them, what treatment can you expect from him, when he is re-inthroned, and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by the Power of <hi>France?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> retiring into <hi>France</hi> after his defeat at the <hi>Boyn,</hi> left the Adminiſtration of his Affairs in <hi>Ireland</hi> to my Lord <hi>Tyrconnel,</hi> and in <hi>Scotland</hi> to the Colonels <hi>Buchan</hi> and <hi>Cannon;</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King having appointed St. <hi>Germain</hi> in <hi>Laye</hi> for his reception, he there began to form a Court in the Year 1690, and his Houſe-hold was conſtituted as follows,
<list>
                  <item>The Duke of <hi>Powis</hi> Lord Chamberlain.</item>
                  <item>Colonel <hi>Porter,</hi> Vice-Chamberlain.</item>
                  <item>Colonel <hi>Skelton,</hi> Comptroller.</item>
                  <item>The Earls of <hi>Dumbarton</hi> and <hi>Abercome,</hi> Lords of the Bed-Chamber.</item>
                  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:52077:5"/>
                  <item>Captains, <hi>Macdonald, Beadles, Stafford,</hi> and <hi>Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanian,</hi> Groom of the Bed-Chamber.</item>
                  <item>The two <hi>Sheldons,</hi> Eſquires.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fergus Graham,</hi> Privy Purſe.</item>
                  <item>Sir <hi>John Sparrow,</hi> Board of Green Cloth, and Mr. <hi>Strickland,</hi> Vice Chamberlain to the Queen.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Officers of State were as follows,</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Brown</hi> (Brother to my Lord <hi>Montague Brown,</hi> and ſometime Commiſſioner of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom) Secretary of State for <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Father <hi>Jnnes,</hi> Preſident of the Scots College at <hi>Paris,</hi> Secretary of State for <hi>Scotland,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Richard Neagle,</hi> Secretary of State for <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>To theſe were added as a Juncto, Mr. <hi>Carril</hi> the Queens Secretary, and Mr. <hi>Stafford,</hi> formerly Envoy at the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> whom the King called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether as a Privy Council to adviſe with upon all Emergencies: The Earl of <hi>Melford</hi> Prime Miniſter of State being ſent to <hi>Rome</hi> ſometime before, partly to Negociate King <hi>James</hi>'s Affairs at the Pope's Court, and partly to remove him from the Jealouſies of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> who at that time wholly Monopolized this Prince's Ear and Favour.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:52077:5"/>
            <p>Thus things continued for a while, but <hi>Ireland</hi> being reduced ſometime after, and the <hi>Scotiſh Highlanders</hi> Submitting, the Court of St. <hi>Germain</hi> was every day thronged with Gentlemen from thoſe Kingdoms, as well as from <hi>England;</hi> and then a Proteſtant Party began to diſtinguiſh themſelves, and endeavour to make an appearance at that Court.</p>
            <p>The firſt conſiderable ſtep they made, was to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire a Chappel from King <hi>James,</hi> for the exerciſe of their Worſhip according to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and propos'd Dr. <hi>Granvile,</hi> Brother to the Earl of <hi>Bath,</hi> formerly Dean of <hi>Durham,</hi> as a fit Perſon to be their Chaplain; they urged the great Incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſuch a Toleration would give to his Adherents in <hi>England,</hi> and what ſatisfaction it would be to ſuch Proteſtants as followed him; but tho' com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Policy, and his Circumſtances made every Body believe that this Requeſt would be eaſily granted, yet it was poſitively denied, and Dr. <hi>Granvile</hi> obliged not only to retire from Court, but alſo from the Town of St. <hi>Germain</hi> to avoid the daily Inſults of the Prieſts, and the dreaded Conſequences of the Jealouſies with which they poſſeſt't King <hi>James</hi>'s Court againſt him. Dr. <hi>Gordon,</hi> a Biſhop of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the only Proteſtant Divine that then was there,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52077:6"/>met with a worſe Treatment ſtill than Dr. <hi>Granvile,</hi> and was reduced to the neceſſity of abjuring his Religion for want of Bread, with which he could not be Supplied, but upon thoſe hard terms. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever K. <hi>James</hi> being ſenſible that ſuch an uſage would prejudice his Intereſt in <hi>Britain,</hi> reſolved to prevent the coming of any Proteſtant Divine there, and therefore ſent Mr. <hi>Macqueen</hi> in Company of Major <hi>Scot</hi> into <hi>England,</hi> who brought Letters from him to his Friends, in which he required them to trouble him no more with Divines, as Meſſengers.</p>
            <p>This bad Succeſs did not altogether diſcourage the Proteſtant Party, they made a ſecond effort up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Conſtitution of the before-mentioned Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil of Five, to have one of the number at leaſt a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant: They inſiſted upon the Advantages which might thence redound to his Majeſties Affairs in <hi>Britain,</hi> and for that end did earneſtly recomend my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Herbert</hi> as a Perſon both well qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified to give Advice in <hi>Engliſh</hi> Affairs, and of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoted reputation in his Country. Thoſe reaſons where ſo convincing, that the <hi>Iriſh</hi> fearing they would obtain their demand; an Information was trumped up againſt the chief Juſtice by Mr. Comptroller <hi>Skelton,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Sharp,</hi> of having ſaid that King
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52077:6"/>
               <hi>James</hi>'s violent Temper would ruin himſelf and all that followed him. My Lord owned the Words, but made ſo ingenious an Explanation of his mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, which was in relation to the Act of Settlement in <hi>Ireland;</hi> that King <hi>James</hi> was ſatisfied. The <hi>Iriſh</hi> having miſſed their Aim, formed a ſhort time after another Plot againſt him, and charged him of correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponding with the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and miſ-repreſenting the Tranſactions of that Court, whereupon he and a worthy Lady, with whom he boarded, were confined, and <hi>Broomfield</hi> the Quaker committed to the <hi>Baſtile.</hi> And thus was this Lord Chief Juſtice for no other reaſon, but his adhering to a Proteſtant Intereſt, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded from all ſhare of management of Affairs in King <hi>James</hi>'s Court tho his Capacity and Sufferings were ſufficient in the Eyes of all reaſonable Men, to have intitled him to a ſhare in that Prince's Favour and Secret. If my Lord Chief Juſtice <hi>Herbert</hi> was ſo uſed, I would fain know upon what ground any of our <hi>Jacobites</hi> ſhould flatter himſelf of a better Treatment.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Cockburn</hi> of <hi>Lanton</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> was the next Proteſtant that had Merit and Favour enough to pretend to a ſhare in the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of King <hi>James</hi>'s Affairs. This Gentleman hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52077:7"/>followed him in <hi>Ireland,</hi> was taken at Sea, after the Battle of the <hi>Boyn,</hi> and brought Piſoner to <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don;</hi> but a Propoſal being made of Exchanging him for Captain <hi>St. Lo,</hi> then Priſoner in <hi>France,</hi> he was inlarged, and during his abode here, did ſo ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiate himſelf with the moſt conſiderable of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected Proteſtants, that he was recommended by them to King <hi>James,</hi> as a Perſon fit to ſerve him in the Affairs of greateſt Truſt. He was no ſooner arived at St. <hi>Germain,</hi> that he told that Prince, his Friends in <hi>England</hi> thought that my Lord <hi>Melford,</hi> who was then returned from <hi>Rome,</hi> was a great Grievance, and ought to be laid aſide, and that the only way for the King to procure the good Opinion of his Subjects in <hi>Britain,</hi> and reconcile them to him, was to put the management of his Affairs in Proteſtants Hands. This prudent Advice of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>affected Proteſtants of <hi>England,</hi> or of Mr. <hi>Cockburn,</hi> had an effect quite contrary to what they expected; King <hi>James</hi> took it ſo ill, that in few days after, an Order was procured from the <hi>French</hi> Court, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding him to depart <hi>France</hi> under ſevere Penal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, being too much a Friend to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Intereſt; Mr. <hi>Cockburn</hi> was forced to obey, and has lived as an Exile in <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Hamburg</hi> ever ſince.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:52077:7"/>
            <p>But the Submiſſion of the <hi>Scotch Highlanders</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford us ſtill ſome more convincing Proofs of King <hi>James</hi>'s hatred for the Proteſtant Religion, and of his Ingratitude towards ſuch who had made a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of all that can be dear to Men, to Support his ſinking Fortune in <hi>Scotland.</hi> The Lords <hi>Dumferling, Dundee, Dunkel,</hi> Colonels <hi>Cannon, Graham,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others Proteſtants, having forfeited their Eſtates and Families, retired into <hi>France,</hi> as alſo did the Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nels <hi>Buchan, Maxwell, Wauchop,</hi> and ſome other Popiſh Gentlemen; but when they came to St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> the Papiſts were immediatly preferred to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Poſts, both in the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Armies, while the Proteſtants, tho their Merit was greater, were expoſed to all imaginable hardſhip, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts: My Lord <hi>Dumferling</hi> and Colonel <hi>Cannon</hi> are too Illuſtrious Examples of King <hi>James</hi>'s Ungra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude, to be here paſt by. The Earl through a miſtaken notion of Loyalty and Honour, had Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed his Honourable Family, and a plentiful Eſtate, to follow that Prince in his misfortune; and it muſt be granted that ſuch a Proof of Loyalty, deſerved ſome kind Returns, yet happening to Quarrel at St. <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main,</hi> with one Captain <hi>Brown</hi> a Papiſt, about a Trifle, the Captain was incouraged and countenanced in his
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52077:8"/>quarrel by the Court, and made Commander of a Company of <hi>Scots,</hi> Reformed Officers in <hi>Catalonia,</hi> whilſt this Noble Lord was deſpiſed, for his adher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to his Religion: This ill Treatment broke his Heart, and he ſunk under the Weight of his hard Fate, at St. <hi>Germain.</hi> His misfortune laſted longer than his Life, for notwithſtanding his Merits, Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, and the Intereſt made by his Friends, he could not obtain a Chriſtian Burial; and his Corps was hid in a Chamber, till an opportunity was found of Digging a hole in the Fields, in the Night, where they Thruſt him in.</p>
            <p>Nor was Colonel <hi>Cannon</hi> better uſed, than my Lord <hi>Dumferling:</hi> This Gentleman Commanded as General over King <hi>James</hi>'s Army in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and ſerved him with ſo much faithfulneſs, that every body thought he would be preferred to a great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, upon his arrival at St. <hi>Germain;</hi> but he po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitively refuſing to abandon the little Religion he had, which was Proteſtant, was reduced to the Scanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Allowance of half a Crown a day, whilſt Papiſts who had ſerved under him, were advanced to good Poſts. This unhappy Gentleman finding himſelf thus neglected, fell ſick through Grief, and Want, and died; having taken the Sacrament from the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:52077:8"/>Hands of Dr. <hi>Granvile,</hi> three days before his Death; but the Prieſt who were always buzing about him, took the oppertunity of his being Speechleſs, to Thruſt a Wafer down his Throat, and gave out that he was dead a Papiſt, and by this means got him the Favour of Burial, which his Corps had elſe been excluded from, as well as my Lord <hi>Dumfer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi>'s. If the Sufferings, and great Merits of theſe two Gentlemen, have not been able to Molify King <hi>James</hi>'s Heart, and to obtain from him any generous Returns, I would fain know upon what Foundation are grounded the great hopes of our Grumblers, ſeeing the moſt part of them have not had Courage enough to follow that Prince, and have, for ought we ſee, no other Qualifications to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commend them, but their bare <hi>Jacobitiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>However, if the Examples I have already expoſed to your view, are not ſufficient, to convince you, that as long as you are Proteſtants, and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Men, you are to expect no ſhare in King <hi>James</hi>'s Favour; I'll produce ſome others, which I am ſure, will open your Eyes, unleſs you are bound by an Oath to continue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways Blind, and I'll begin with Sir <hi>James Mountgomerie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Gentleman left no Stone unturn'd to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtabliſh King <hi>James</hi> in <hi>Scotland,</hi> by the ſame Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:52077:9"/>that declared him to have Forfeited his Right: He was afterward, for ſeveral Years, his moſt Active Miniſter in <hi>England,</hi> Penn'd and Publiſh'd Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for him, at the time of his deſigned Deſcent from <hi>La Hogue,</hi> and after the Miſcarriage of that, wrote his <hi>Britain's juſt Complaints:</hi> Was his weekly <hi>News ſender,</hi> and <hi>Project Drawer;</hi> yet this very Sir <hi>James Mountgomerie,</hi> who had done ſuch great things, and run ſuch hazards for him, being obliged to fly to <hi>France,</hi> after making his eſcape from the Meſſengers Houſe, could not obtain, by reaſon of his being a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, any ſhare into that Prince's Favour; was brow-beaten from the Court by Prieſts, daily up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided with having been once in the Prince of <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>range</hi>'s Intereſt, and at laſt Obliged to retire to <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> where he dyed with the Melancholy Reflections of the miſerable State he brought himſelf into.</p>
            <p>The Earl of <hi>Lauderdale,</hi> tho a Papiſt, met with no better Fate than Sir <hi>James:</hi> His Lady being a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, and he an enemy to the violent Meaſures of the Court; was judged to be a ſufficient Reaſon to exclude him from any ſhare in the Government; ſo natural it is for all Bigots to hate every body that will not go to their height of Violence. This Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman heartily adviſed King <hi>James</hi> to put his Affairs
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52077:9"/>into Proteſtants Hands, and recommended the Earl of <hi>Cl—n,</hi> and the Nonjuring Biſhops in <hi>England,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Home, Southerk,</hi> and <hi>Sinclair</hi> in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> as the fitteſt Perſons to ſerve him, but his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice was ſo ill taken, that he had his Lady ſent to <hi>England,</hi> not to return any more; was himſelf for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid the Court, and reduced to a Penſion of one Hundred Piſtols <hi>per Annum:</hi> He retired to <hi>Paris,</hi> and ſeeing no Probability of his Maſters changing his Meaſures, died of Grief. One would have thought that his Brother, Mr. <hi>Alexander Maitland,</hi> who on ſeveral Occaſions had behaved himſelf very bravely, in that Prince's Service, ſhould have been Preferred by him, yet he met with ſuch an Entertainment, that wanting Bread there, he was very glad to come to <hi>England,</hi> and make his Peace with the Government, whoſe Service he had Deſerted, having once had a Command in the <hi>Scots</hi> Guards, under King <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Andrew Forreſter,</hi> is another great Inſtance of King <hi>James</hi>'s averſion to Proteſtants: This Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man ſerved with all imaginable Zeal, that Prince's Intereſts when a Subject, and was the devoted Creature of his moſt Arbitrary Commands, when a King; he ſuffered Impriſonment in the <hi>Tower</hi> for
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52077:10"/>him, at the time of his deſigned Deſcent, and yet notwithſtanding all this, and the great Experience he had in <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Affairs, he could never obtain any ſhare in that Prince's Confidence: When he came to St. <hi>Germain,</hi> all his Merits, Sufferings, and the good Character he had in both Kingdoms, were not enough to Counter-ballance, the Objection of being a Proteſtant, and therefore by no means to be Intruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; ſo that after ſome times Attendance, as a Cypher, he was rewarded with a Paſs to return to <hi>England,</hi> for they had there no occaſion for him.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Theophilus Oglethorp,</hi> who by his Capacity as well as Services, was incouraged to go over, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer his Aſſiſtance, met with Sir <hi>Andrew Forreſter</hi>'s Fate upon account of his Religion; and was ſo unkindly uſed, that he was very glad to get home to Old <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> again, where, 'tis expected, he will Plot no more.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Fergus Graham</hi> was the only Proteſtant Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman in King <hi>James</hi>'s Family, but as ſoon as they ſaw that my Lord <hi>Preſton,</hi> and Colonel <hi>Graham</hi> his Brothers, who ventured ſo much for that Prince, could do them no more Service in <hi>England,</hi> he was diſcharged for no other Reaſon, but that they thought a Proteſtant a Blemiſh in their Houſe-hold.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:52077:10"/>
            <p>Nor was Sir <hi>William Sharp</hi> better uſed, altho he pretended to come over upon the Act of Parliament in <hi>Scotland,</hi> to ſave his Eſtate, for the Entertainment he had at St. <hi>Germain</hi> before he came away, is very well known. The Penſion he had whilſt King <hi>James</hi>'s Army in <hi>Scotland</hi> kept up, was taken from him, and he fell under diſtruſts, with <hi>Melford</hi> and <hi>Jnnes,</hi> and contempt at Court, which will appear to all Reaſonable Men a Sufficient motive for his coming away.</p>
            <p>But the uſage of Dr. <hi>Cockburn</hi> a <hi>Scotiſh</hi> Divine, is beyond any thing that can be imagined. This Gentleman was Baniſhed <hi>Scotland</hi> for his Practices againſt the Government, and afterwards being ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to leave <hi>England,</hi> for writing of Pamphlets, thought himſelf ſecure of a Sanctuary at St. <hi>Germain,</hi> if not, of a Reward for his Services; but inſtead of that he met with the daily importunities of Prieſts, to make him abandon his Religion, and their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours proving vain, they then repreſented him as a dangerous Perſon, and got him ſent from <hi>France.</hi> He lives now an Exile in <hi>Holland,</hi> both from <hi>Britain</hi> and <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mrs. <hi>Aſhton,</hi> Widow to Mr. <hi>Aſhton,</hi> who was Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted for his being concerned in my Lord <hi>Preſton</hi>'s
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52077:11"/>Affairs, went to the Court of St. <hi>Germain,</hi> after her Husband's Death, as thinking that ſhe had ſome Merit to plead for a kind Reception, but ſhe was as much deceived as any of thoſe I have already menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned. Few days after her arrival, Prieſts were ſent to tell her, that nothing but being a Roman Catholick could recommend a Woman to the Queen's Service, which the Poor Gentlewoman declining to comply with, was neglected, and dying ſoon after, was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd Burial, till her Father Mr. <hi>Rigby</hi> of <hi>Covent-Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> as a mighty Favour, and at great Charges, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained leave from the Court of St. <hi>Germain,</hi> to have her body brought over into <hi>England;</hi> and Buried her in <hi>Covent-Garden</hi> Church.</p>
            <p>If theſe Examples are not ſufficient to convince our <hi>Jacobites,</hi> or if they queſtion the Truth of them, for really I muſt own, that they are almoſt incredible; I deſire them to conſult the Young Lord <hi>Henmore,</hi> Mr. <hi>Louthian,</hi> Captains <hi>Murray, Dalyel, Macgil, Maclean, Fielding,</hi> Mr. <hi>Charles Kinnaird,</hi> and ſeveral hundreds more, now in and about <hi>London,</hi> who are lately come from St. <hi>Germain,</hi> and they will tell you, that the only Reaſon why they left that Court, was, becauſe they could not have Bread, except they would change their Religion, and therefore did chooſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52077:11"/>to run the hazard of Impriſonment, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning to <hi>England,</hi> than ſtay and Starve in <hi>France.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many Inſtances more might be given, to ſhew King <hi>James</hi>'s hatred to every thing, that bears the name of Proteſtant; but if what has already been ſaid, is not ſufficient, ſure I am, that the reſt ſhould be to no purpoſe: What Proteſtant has he ever ſo much as ſeemed to Truſt, ſince he lives in <hi>France?</hi> I know that my Lord <hi>Middleton</hi> muſt be excepted, for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed King <hi>James</hi> has a ſeeming Truſt in him. There is no Man that has been at St. <hi>Germain,</hi> but muſt needs perceive, that he is not chief Miniſter, as <hi>Melford</hi> was, nor manages Affairs betwixt <hi>Verſailles</hi> and St. <hi>Germain,</hi> that being done by <hi>Innes</hi> and <hi>Porter:</hi> He is but ſeldom cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to the Council, and the <hi>French</hi> Court has never depended upon his Corriſpondence, ſince the diſappointment they receive by our Fleets going into the <hi>Streights.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I hope, theſe Inſtances will convince all good Men, that have any Senſe of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, Religion, and Honour, how unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:52077:12"/>it is to be a <hi>Jacobite,</hi> and to think that the Preſent Misfortunes of King <hi>James,</hi> will Frighten him from Invading our Laws and Liberties in time to come, ſeeing, that neither the abandoning of Wives, Children, and Eſtates, nor the hazarding, nay, loſs of Life in his Service, can render him Juſt and Favourable to ſuch Proteſtants, who have made a Sacrifice of all thoſe things to follow him: And if it be ſo, as certainly it is, what muſt thoſe Proteſtant Nations expect, (if ever he re-obtains the Government, who have renounced him, and ſet another Prince upon his Throne?</p>
            <p>If theſe, who have followed him into <hi>France,</hi> are denied the Exerciſe of their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, when his Circumſtances make it his Intereſt to grant it, what muſt we expect if ever he be again in Poſſeſſion of the Crown?</p>
            <p>My Lord chief Juſtice <hi>Herbert,</hi> and the other Gentlemen before-named, who firmly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to his Intereſts, even in his greateſt Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, were contemned, deſpiſed, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:52077:12"/>to Starve, becauſe they were Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants; how can we, or any Proteſtant <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobites,</hi> who have none of thoſe Merits, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be better uſed? If the loſs of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and Eſtates, has not been ſufficient to obtain from him Chriſtian Burial; upon what Ground can our <hi>Jacobites,</hi> who have done nothing for him, flatter themſelves with the hopes of great Preferments, if he is rein<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned? In ſhort, if the Example he had of his Father's Misfortunes, and his Brothers Exile, wherein he himſelf was a ſharer, together with the Senſe of his own Misfortunes, have not been able to work a Reformation upon him, as appears by the above-written Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; can we expect that he ever will be made more Plyable?</p>
            <p>The Education of his Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> whom no body doubts he deſigns his Succeſſor, is is another Inſtance of his irreconciliable Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy to the Proteſtant Religion, and <hi>Engliſh</hi> Liberties: One would have thought that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, as well as Policy, would have made him educate his Child a Proteſtant, or at leaſt oblige him to put Proteſtants about him, of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52077:13"/>unqueſtioned Reputation, to inſtruct him in the ways of pleaſing the People, but in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of that, Dr. <hi>Beeſon,</hi> a famous and violent Papiſt, was made his Preceptor, and none but Popiſh Servants are allowed to be about him, ſo that he can imbibe nothing but what is for the Intereſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> and Deſtruction of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Can People be ſo mad as to expect good terms from a Prince, who not only thus Treats his Proteſtant Subjects, who have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him in his Misfortune, but alſo whoſe Religion lays him under a Neceſſity of doing it? Could greater Obligations be laid upon any Prince, than were upon him, by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> when a Subject? Her In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt Saved him from being proſecuted for the Popiſh Plot, excluded from the Succeſſion to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne, and afterwards de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throned by the Duke of <hi>Monmouth,</hi> yet all thoſe Obligations were no more than his Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion Oath, could not hinder him from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading the Proteſtant Religion in general, but more particularly the Liberties of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:52077:13"/>
            <p>But perhaps ſome will Object againſt what I have ſaid, that from the Entertainment Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants meet with at St. <hi>Germain,</hi> 'tis not reaſonnable to conclude, that King <hi>James</hi> bears ſtill ſuch an averſion to our Religion and Liberties: For being himſelf but a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugee</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and having nothing to live upon but the Penſion the <hi>French</hi> King al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows him, it is not in his Power to reward thoſe Proteſtants who have followed him, even not to careſs them; and therefore we ought rather to Peruſe the Declarations he has put out ſince his being in <hi>France,</hi> for therein we ſhall find undeniable Proofs, that his Misfortunes have much altered his Mind. Read (will our <hi>Jacobites</hi> ſay) the Declaration he Publiſhed upon his intended Deſcent from <hi>La Hogue,</hi> and Obſerve what promiſes he makes, both in relation to our Religion and our Liberties, the Sincerity whereof, you have no manner of pretence to Queſtion, for then, thinking himſelf ſure of his Game, nothing could oblige him to diſguiſe the true Sentiments of his Heart.</p>
            <pb n="22" facs="tcp:52077:14"/>
            <p>This is ſomewhat indeed, Gentlemen, and were the thing as you ſay, I would agree with you, but give me leave to tell you, that 'tis a great Queſtion, whether the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration you ſpeak of, which was Printed here, did really contain King <hi>James</hi>'s Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents; but whether it was his own De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, or Sir <hi>James Mountgomerie</hi>'s, it does not matter a Pin, for his late Majeſty did Publickly diſown it in a Memorial to the <hi>Pope,</hi> upon his return to <hi>Paris;</hi> and it has been acknowledged in a <hi>Jacobite</hi> Pamphlet, called, <hi>An Anſwer to Dr. Wellwood's Anſwer, to King</hi> James<hi>'s Declaration;</hi> That the ſame was formed without his Knowledge, and againſt his Inclination.</p>
            <p>I have told you, in the beginning of this Diſcourſe, that I believe that there are among you ſome Conſcientious Men, and to thoſe I ſhall ſay nothing at this time, but to ſuch that are Angry with the Government, (as I know many amongſt you are) meerly becauſe they cannot have any Imployment under it, and who think without any further Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52077:14"/>to better their Condition, by a Second Revolution: I'll ſay, that they ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, that King <hi>James</hi>'s Popiſh Friends, muſt be all provided for firſt of all, and pray what will remain then for you? For as to Penſions, I think you are not ſo mad as to flatter your ſelves with ſuch imaginary hopes, for the <hi>French</hi> Army that brings King <hi>James</hi> over muſt be paid, and their vaſt Charges for the <hi>Iriſh</hi> War, and the Maintenance of King <hi>James</hi> re-imburſed, before your beloved Prince be in a condition to expreſs his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to you: perhaps you will ſay, that the <hi>French</hi> King is too much a Gentleman, to demand any ſuch thing, but I don't know what has given you that Noble Idea of his Generoſity; but ſuppoſing his Temper to be ſuch, this War will ſo much drain his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequer, that Neceſſity will force him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand what is ſo juſtly owing to him, and who ſhall be able to diſpute his Bill of Charges? Nay, will King <hi>James</hi> be able to ſatisfy him? I don't know, but this I am ſure of, that as long as you profeſs the Proteſtant Religion, you cannot expect to be more Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourably
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:52077:15"/>Treated then his preſent Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers.</p>
            <p>Some others amongſt you are diſaffected, becauſe, as they ſay, without the Reſtoration of King <hi>James,</hi> a Proteſtant War will be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailed on the Nation, and becauſe our Treaſure is exhauſted by Taxes, and our Blood expended beyond Sea, which the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion cannot long bear.</p>
            <p>To theſe Gentlemen, I muſt anſwer, that they are much miſtaken, for the bringing in of King <hi>James,</hi> which they think will put an end to theſe Troubles, would infallibly bring the Seat of War from <hi>Flanders</hi> into <hi>England:</hi> For it is unreaſonable to Suppoſe, that ſo many Noble-men and Gentlemen as are ingaged in King <hi>William</hi>'s Cauſe, would tamely Submit, or that his Majeſty, whoſe Intereſt in <hi>Europe</hi> is ſo very great, would either ingloriouſly abandon his Throne, or want Foreign Aſſiſtance to Support him in it.</p>
            <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52077:15"/>
            <p n="2">2. King <hi>James</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> King are both Old, and upon a change of a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in <hi>France,</hi> we may reaſonably expect change of Meaſures; for as to the Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> his Intereſt ſtands or fall, with that of his Suppoſed Father; but after all, is it reaſonable to believe that the <hi>French</hi> or any other Nation, will live in perpetual War with us, meerly for the ſake of a Prince, who pretends to be deprived of his Rights? There are very few <hi>Knights-Errants</hi> in this Age, or at leaſt, ſure I am; that no Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n general is Acted by their Principles, and we ſee the <hi>French</hi> offer already to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake him.</p>
            <p n="3">3. I Grant that our Taxes are greater then ever our Nation paid, but yet they are not ſo heavy but that we can hold it out, many Years at this Rate. In ſhort, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they be, I believe there is no good Man but will rather hazard his Perſon to keep the Enemy abroad, than ſee a <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Army in the Bowels of our own Country, deſtroying our Subſtance, burning
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52077:16"/>our Habitations, and committing the Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities which they committed in the <hi>Palatinate:</hi> For certainly by one Months Ravage of this Nature, we ſhould loſe more Blood and Treaſure, than can probably be ſpent to bring the War to an Honourable and happy Concluſion.</p>
            <p>That happy Moment is not perhaps ſo far as ſome People imagine; for whoſoever will caſt his Eyes on the preſent Poſturs of Affairs in <hi>Europe,</hi> muſt needs conclude that the <hi>French</hi> cannot hold it out much longer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:52077:16"/>
            <head>BOOKS <hi>Sold by</hi> Richard Baldwin.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>BIbliotheca Politica:</hi> Or an Enquiry into the Antient Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Engliſh Government; with reſpect both to the juſt Extent of Regal Power, and to the Rights and Liberties of the Subject: Wherein all the chief Arguments, as well againſt as for the late Revolution, are impartially repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented and conſidered. In XIII. Dialogues. Collected out of the beſt Authors both Ancient and Modern. To which is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded an Alphabetical Index to the whole Work.</p>
            <p>The Works of <hi>F. Rabelais,</hi> M. D. in five Books; or the Lives, Heroick Deeds and Sayings of the good <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gantua</hi> and <hi>Pantagruel,</hi> and his Voyage to the Oracle of the Bottle. As alſo his Hiſtorical Letters. To which is ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Author's Life, and Explanatory Remarks. By Mr. <hi>Motteux.</hi> Never before Printed in <hi>Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The World Bewitch'd</hi> containing an Examination of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Opinions concerning Spirits, their Nature, Power, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, and Operations; as alſo the Effects Men are able to produce by their Communication. Divided into four Parts. By <hi>Belthazer Bekker,</hi> D. D. and Paſtor at <hi>Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</hi> Vol. I. Tranſlated from a <hi>French</hi> Copy, approv'd of, and ſubſcribed by the Author's own Hand.</p>
            <p>A Collection of Speeches of the Right Honourable <hi>Henry</hi> late Earl of <hi>Warrington, viz.</hi> I. His Speech upon his being ſwore Mayor of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> in <hi>November</hi> 1691. II. His Speech to the Grand-Jury at <hi>Cheſter, April</hi> 13, 1692. III. His Charge to the Grand-Jury at the Quarter-Seſſions held for the County of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> on the 11th of <hi>October,</hi> 1692. IV. His Charge to the Grand-Jury at the Quarter-Seſſions held for the County of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> on the 25th of <hi>April,</hi> 1693.</p>
            <p>Letters of State, written by Mr. <hi>John Milton,</hi> to moſt of the Sovereign Princes and Republicks of <hi>Europe,</hi> from the Year 1649, to the Year 1659. To which is added, an Account of his Life. Together with ſeveral of his Poems; and a Catalogue of his Works, never before Printed.</p>
            <p>An Anſwer to a Paper written by Count <hi>d' Avaux,</hi> the <hi>French</hi> King's Ambaſſador in <hi>Sweden,</hi> concerning the Propoſals of Peace made by <hi>France</hi> to the Confederates.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
